William F. Miller Papers SC0231
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
William F. Miller Papers
1957-2013
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Miller, William F.
SC0231
5.75 Linear Feet
The collection consists of the professional and personal papers of Dr. William F. Miller including Provost's correspondence and memos, private correspondence, policy and memos, appointment books and date notebooks, talks given by Miller, articles written by Miller, photographs, news clippings and news releases.
Biographical/Historical note
William F. Miller received is BS (1949), MS (1951), PhD (1956) and Honorary DSc (1972) from Purdue University. He was the last faculty member recruited to Stanford University by the legendary Frederick Terman, who was then Vice President and Provost of Stanford. Miller himself later became Vice President and Provost of Stanford. He conducted research and directed many graduate students in Computer Science. As President and CEO of SRI International (1979-1990) Miller opened SRI to the Pacific Region; he established the spin-out and commercialization program at SRI and established the David Sarnoff Research Center (now the Sarnoff Corporation) as a for-profit subsidiary of SRI, and he became the Chairman and CEO of SRI. In 1982 Miller was appointed to the National Science Board. He has served on the board of directors of several major companies such as Signetics, Firemans Fund Insurance, First Interstate Bank (and later) Wells Fargo Bank, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, Varian Associates, WhoWhere? Inc. (Chairman), and Borland Software Corp. (Chairman). He co-founded SmartValley, Inc. and aided the formation of CommerceNet and serves on the board of directors. Dr. Miller was a founding director of the Center for Excellence in Non-profits. He currently serves as Chairman of the Board of Sentius Corporation and is a Founder and Chairman of Nanostellar, Inc. Dr. Miller is a Life Member of the National Academy of Engineering, Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Science, Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Life Fellow of IEEE, and Member of the Silicon Valley Engineering Hall of Fame.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the professional and personal papers of Dr. William F. Miller including Provost's correspondence and memos, private correspondence, policy and memos, appointment books and date notebooks, talks given by Miller, articles written by Miller, photographs, news clippings and news releases.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Stanford University -- Administration.; Miller, William F.
- Provost's Personal Correspondence and Memos, 1970-1979; Series 1
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1978 January-June (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1978 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1978 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Resignation as Provost, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Announcement of his appointment as SRI President, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - Incoming re: appointment as SRI President, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - Outgoing re: appointment as SRI President, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence - Visiting committee to Tulane, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Private and Confidential Correspondence, 1970-1979; Series 2
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Policy Memos, Office of the Provost, 1971-1978; Series 3
  - Institutional, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Support Services, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Academic/Administrative Interface, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Affairs, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Administrative Affairs, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Provosts Staff, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Provostial Style, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Provost and Deans, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Academic Affairs, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Appointments, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Affairs, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Old Programs, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - New Programs, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fundraising, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Staff Affairs, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Environmental Affairs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Institutional, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Support Services, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Student Affairs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Affirmative Action, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Administrative/Academic Interface, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Provost Staff, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Provostial Style, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Provost and Deans, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Academic Affairs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Faculty Appointments, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Faculty Affairs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Professoriate, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Old Programs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - New Programs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Fundraising, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Staff Affairs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Environmental Relations, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Institutional, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Support Services, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Students, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Affirmative Action, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Administrative/Academic Interface, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Administrative Maintenance, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Provost Staff, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Provostial Style, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Provost and Deans, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Academic Affairs, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Faculty Appointments, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Professoriate, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Old Programs, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - New Programs, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Staff Affairs, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Fundraising, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Environmental Relations, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Institutional, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Support Services, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Students, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Affirmative Action, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Administrative/Academic Interface, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Provost/Staff, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Provostial Style, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Provost and Deans, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Academic Affairs, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Faculty Appointments, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Professoriate, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Old Programs, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - New Programs, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Staff Affairs, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Fundraising, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Environmental Relations, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Highlights, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Institutional, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Support Services, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Students, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Affirmative Action, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Administrative/Academic Interface, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Administrative Maintenance, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Provost/Staff, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Provostial Style, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Provost and Deans, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Academic Affairs, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Faculty Appointments, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Staff Affairs, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Old Programs, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Environmental Relations, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Institutional, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Support Services, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Students, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Administrative/Academic Interface, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Administrative Maintenance, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Provost/Staff, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Provostial Style, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Academic Affairs, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Faculty Affairs, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Staff Affairs, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Environmental Affairs, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Fundraising, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Institutional, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Support Services, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Administrative/Academic Interface, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Administrative Maintenance, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Provost/Staff, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Provostial Style, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Academic Affairs, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Faculty Appointments, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Faculty Affairs, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Environmental Affairs, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Fundraising, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Institutional, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Support Services, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Administrative/Academic Interface, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Administrative Affairs, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Provost/Staff, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Provostial Style, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Provost and Deans, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Staff Affairs, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Academic Affairs, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Faculty Affairs, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Faculty Affairs, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Environmental Affairs, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Fundraising, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 117)
- Appointment Books, 1971-1978; Series 4
  - Appointment Books, 1971-1978 (Box 4)
- Notebooks, 1970-1979; Series 5
  - Date calendars, 1970-1979 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Files, 1972-1979; Series 6
  - William F. Miller current professional vita, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Argonne National Laboratories, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bonner, William S., Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - International Institute For Applied Systems Analysis, Laxenburg, Austria, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Massey, William F., Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Perron, William F., Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Purdue University, Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Students, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Material for 1979 calendar (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Annual report, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Report of the Committee on the Professoriate at Stanford, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Microelectronics and computer, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Notes 1, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Notes 2, Undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Talks, 1971-1979; Series 7
  - General, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - General, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - General, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Senate and Academic Council, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Senate and Academic Council, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Senate and Academic Council, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Senate and Academic Council, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Senate and Academic Council, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Senate and Academic Council, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Talks to Alumni, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Talks to Alumni, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Talks to Students, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Old Presentations, Undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Palm Springs Speech, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Misc. Speech Welcoming a Seminar - "New Perspectives on the Safety of Dams", 1978 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Speeches, 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Articles, 1957-1980; Series 8
  - "On the Theory of Inelastic Scattering of Electrons by Helium Atoms", 1957 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "Efficiencies and Photofractions for Sodium-Iodide Crystals", 1957 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Efficiencies and Photofractions for Gamma Radiation on Sodium Iodide Crystals", 1959 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "The Use of High Speed Digital Computers for the Least Squares Calculation of Complexity Constants", 1959 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "The Use of High Speed Digital Computers for the Least Squares Calculation of Complexity Constants", 1959 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "Design Calculations for NaI Systems", 1960 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Response Spectra for Gamma Rays in CSI", 1960 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Monte Carlo Calculation of Neutron Evaporation; Excitation Energy Dependence of Nuclear Level Density., Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Energy-Dependent Multiple Scattering of Neutrons in Thin Plates, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - The Role of Computers in Experimental Physics: A System for On-Line Analyzers, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The GNS Multicomputer System, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - "Encyclopedic Dictionary of Physics" (excerpt), Undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - "Who's Who at Stanford" and Chaffe unpublished dissertation, 1978-1980 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Scope and Contents note
    Chaffe, Ellen. "Decision Models in University Budgeting." Stanford, 1980. (Unpublished Ph.D. dissertation). Chapter 4 (regarding Miller's administration).
  - Miscellaneous magazines, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Stanford GSB, Winter 1978-1979; EDUCOM, Winter 1978
- Photographs, 1967-1979; Series 9
  - Photographs, 1967-1970 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Photographs, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Photographs, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Photographs, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Photographs, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Photographs, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Newsclippings and News Releases, 1969-1978; Series 10
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Newsclippings and News Releases, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2018-095
  - Miller, William, "Metastable Atoms in Rare Gases" (MS Thesis, Purdue), 1951 Aug (Box 1)
  - Miller, William, "A Theoretical Study of Excitation and Ionization by Electrons in Helium and of the Mean Energy Per Ion Pair" (Ph.D. Thesis, Purdue), 1956 Jan (Box 1)
  - System Scope for Library Automation and Generalized Information Storage and Retrieval at Stanford University, 1970 Feb (Box 1)
  - The Libraries of Stanford University: 1990 and Beyond, 1980 Apr (Box 1)
  - Stanford University Annual Financial Report, 1972 (Box 1)
  - IEEE Transactions, 1963 Dec (Box 1)
  - Impact: Stanford University's Economic Impact via Innovation & Entreneurship, 2012 Mar (Box 1)
  - The Gus Multicomputer System, 1963 Dec (Box 1)
  - Publications/Reprints, 1966-2013 (Box 2)